One of the most common ways to measure the spread
إحدى الطرق الأكثر شيوعًا لقياس انتشار
of our data is by looking at the Five Number Summary,
بياناتنا هي بالنظر إلى Five Number Summary،
which gives us values for calculating the range and interquartile range.
والذي يعطينا قيمًا لحساب النطاق والمدى الربيعي.
The Five Number Summary consists of five values, the maximum,
يتكون Five Number Summary من خمس قيم، الحد الأقصى،
the minimum, the first quartile,
والحد الأدنى، والربع الأول،
the second quartile which is also the median, and the third quartile.
والربع الثاني الذي هو أيضًا الوسيط، والربع الثالث.
Consider we have the following dataset.
ينبغي مراعاة أن لدينا مجموعة البيانات التالية.
The first thing we need to do to calculate
أول شيء يتعين علينا القيام به لحساب
the Five Number Summary is to order our values.
Five Number Summary هو ترتيب قيمنا.
Once ordered, the minimum and the maximum values
وبمجرد ترتيب القيم، يكون من السهل تحديد القيمة الدنيا والقيمة القصوى
are easy to identify as the smallest and largest values.
باعتبارها القيمة الأصغر والأكبر.
As we calculate it in the section on measures of center,
نظرًا لأننا نحسبها في قسم مقاييس المركز،
the median is the middle value in our dataset.
فإن الوسيط هو القيمة المتوسطة في مجموعة البيانات.
We also call this Q2 or the second quartile because
كما نسمي هذا الربع الثاني أو Q2 لأن
50% of our data or two quarters fall below this value.
50٪ من بياناتنا أو ربعين من هذه البيانات تقل عن هذه القيمة.
The remaining two values to complete the Five Number Summary are Q1 and Q3.
القيمتان المتبقيتان لاستكمال Five Number Summary هما Q1 و Q3.
These values can be thought of as the medians of the data on either side of Q2.
يمكن اعتبار هذه القيم كوسيطة للبيانات على جانبي Q2.
That is the median of these data points is Q1,
هذا هو متوسط​نقاط البيانات هذه في Q1،
this value is such that 25% of our data fall below it,
وهذه القيمة هي أن 25٪ من بياناتنا تقع أسفلها،
and the median of these data points is Q3 or the third quartile.
وأن وسيط نقاط البيانات هذه هو Q3 أو الربع الثالث.
This value is such that 75% of our data fall below this mark.
هذه القيمة هي أن 75 ٪ من بياناتنا تقع تحت هذه العلامة.
Notice, Q2 was not an either a set of these points used to calculate Q1 or Q3.
لاحظوا أن Q2 لم يكن مجموعة من هذه النقاط المستخدمة لحساب Q1 أو Q3.
This provides our Five Number Summary as the following.
هذا يعطينا Five Number Summary كما يلي.
Let's consider another example for in our dataset has an even set of values.
لنأخذ مثال آخر في مجموعة بياناتنا الخاصة التي تحتوي على مجموعة متساوية من القيم.
Again, we first need to order the values.
مرة أخرى، نحتاج أولاً إلى ترتيب القيم.
We can quickly identify the maximum and the minimum.
يمكننا تحديد القيمة القصوى والقيمة الدنيا بسرعة.
Remember, with an even number of values,
تذكر، أنه في حال كون القيم عددًا زوجيًا،
the median or Q2 is given as the mean of these two values here.
يُحدد الوسيط أو Q2 باعتباره متوسط هاتين القيمتين هنا.
In order to find Q1 and Q3,
ولإيجاد Q1 و Q3،
we divide our dataset between the two values we use to find the median.
نقسم مجموعة بياناتنا بين القيمتين التي نستخدمها لإيجاد الوسيط.
This provides these two datasets.
وهذا يعطينا هاتين المجموعتين من البيانات.
Finding the median of each of these will provide Q1 and Q3.
سيوفر إيجاد الوسيط لكل منهما الربعين Q1 و Q3.
For this dataset, Q1 will be the mean of these two values,
بالنسبة إلى مجموعة البيانات هذه، سيكون Q1 متوسط​هاتين القيمتين
and Q3, will be the mean of these two values.
وسيكون Q3 متوسط​هاتين القيمتين.
This provides our Five Number Summary as the following.
هذا يعطينا Five Number Summary كما يلي.
Once we've calculated all the values for the Five Number Summary,
وبمجرد حساب جميع القيم لـ Five Number Summary،
finding the range and interquartile range is no problem.
فإن إيجاد النطاق والمدي الربيعي لا يمثل مشكلة.
For the first dataset,
بالنسبة لمجموعة البيانات الأولى،
the range is calculated as the maximum minus the minimum.
يتم حساب النطاق على أنه القيمة القصوى مطروحًا منها القيمة الدنيا.
this was 10 minus 1 or 9.
كانت هذه القيمة 10 ناقص 1، أو 9.
And the interquartile range is calculated as Q3 minus Q1,
ويتم حساب المدي الربيعي بطرح Q1 من Q3،
which is 8 minus 2 or 6.
أي 8 ناقص 2، أو 6.